Exercise 2 Balance The Circle of Possibilities
Assume a comfortable position and begin your process of
attaining a state of deep meditation.
As before, we start in emptiness, floating free and completely
at ease.
The mundane world is melting away into nothingness, and your
concerns for the day are washing away with it. Be still for
a time and enjoy this moment. moment.
You feel yourself slowly floating downward, softly, slowly,
floating towards your domain. rain.
You feel a sensation of power flow over you like a warm
bath, soothing and protecting you as you pass through it.
You are crossing over into the shadow realm.
Nothingness slowly gives way to twilight and you float downward
past a simple orb of glass that contains within it a key.
You pay little attention to this orb As you know that it
is not yet time To discover its purpose and its meaning
You see the mighty walls of stone That encircle your realm You
are comforted by their presence
You float ever downward Further and further Until finally you
come to rest Between two pools of power And a great mirror
of promise and magic
You can hear the subtle bubbling and churning of the unknowable
waters that make up the mirror, and you gaze upon it with
hope and anticipation.
But you see nothing in the glass.
Suddenly you get the familiar feeling of having left something
undone.
What could it be?
All at once a fierce torrid of wind blasts by you, pushing
you sideways with its force.
You stand and try to brace yourself against this mighty wind,
but its course changes direction and the winds begin to encircle
you.
Within the swirling flow of the mighty winds, you can hear
voices,
some loud and some but a whisper.
These voices see -saw back and forth, as if they were phasing
blazing in and out of reality.
The sound of the circling winds is thunderous as it whips about
you and throughout your realm.
You feel as if you are standing in the center of a
tornado.
You move towards its spinning mass, feeling as though you could
pluck knowledge of anything you wish to learn from inside this
tornado.
But as you begin to move, a powerful blast of heat stays
you in your path.
A jet of flame passes over you and yet you are not
burned by it.
Instead you begin to feel an amazing courage and desire growing
within your breast.
The stream of flame intensifies and its warmth impassions your
spirit. The flame quickly grows into a massive wall of fire and
it merges with a swirling circle of winds and a vast eruption
of power.
The feeling of something approaching from behind distracts you.
As you turn to face it, a wave of blue -green water
washes all around you.
Your breath halts in your throat, and you begin to tremble, as
every emotion you have ever known fills you all at once.
A thousand voices resound in your mind, and you can understand
what every one of them is saying, as the peace of understanding
flows through your entire being, you become steady.
The last of the mighty wave of water flows around you and
washes against the wall of fire and wind, joining with it
seamlessly.
You are held in wonder at the unimaginable sight before you.
Finger -like cyclones of energy are beginning to pulse in and
out from the spinning wall as it wheels ever faster around you.
Its pull is intense and commanding. You begin to wonder if you
are going to be pulled into the energy storm.
You hear a tremendous crunching and cracking all around you. It
is as if a huge tree is about to crash to the
ground.
Leaves and branches seem to come from nowhere and bombard the
walls of the tempest, only to be drawn into its spinning mass.
An ever -increasing deluge of debris is now flying past you.
you.
Pieces of stone and earth join the frenzied current of branches
and leaves smashing into the wall. They are increasing in size
and are passing dangerously close to you. You start to question
your safety.
Your concern is heightened as the monstrous rumbling of what
could only be an avalanche swells throughout the realm.
huge boulders and entire trees are now being sucked into the
vortex of the wall it is as if an entire mountain is
being ripped apart around you feelings of panic threaten to
overtake you but you are strong you still yourself now you begin
to listen more carefully to what is within the mighty noise all
around you.
From deep within the destructive deluge of the avalanche, you
hear the unmistakable sounds of a peaceful meadow.
The song of a breeze gently blowing through tall grass surrounds
you.
The soft chirping of birds and the smell of fertile green earth
envelop you. you.
All at once you feel grounded and at one with all life
within the meadow.
You lie down in the soft grass of this peaceful place and
you begin to dream.
Something stirs you, you awaken in the shadow realm, but the
sight before your eyes makes you wonder if you are not still
dreaming.
The tornado of energy has vanished completely, you can see that
it has left behind a few few gifts.
You find yourself surrounded by four huge stone statues arranged
evenly around you in a circle.
They have been sculpted to represent the magical elements of
earth, air, fire, and water.
In the center of each of these elemental statues is a slowly
spinning portal to the domain from which it came, and each glows
with a different color of ghostly spectral light.
Have you learned the lessons of the elements? A fragile, yet
familiar voice asks you.
As you turn towards this voice, you find a curious sight.
An old woman is rising up and out of the pool of
the moon.
As she steps from it, she looks at you with a pleasing
smile and twinkling eyes. You recognize her as one of the people
Who have touched you most deeply in your life
Balance A gruff yet somehow very gentle voice bellows
You have heard this voice many times before
You turn again and greet the elderly gentleman Rising from the
pool of the sun
You give him a gracious nod And you can feel in your
heart Just how much he means to you
You are comforted yet very confused by the presence of these two
in the shadow realm. You gesture toward them as if to ask
a wordless question, but suddenly they are no longer the only
ones there.
One by one you see other beings rise from the two pools.
Some are human, some are not.
Some you have known your entire life, some you have never seen
before. Some are creatures of myth and fantasy, some you can't
quite make out at all.
As they rise from the two pools, each being gives you a
knowing glance.
Now they begin to encircle you from two different directions.
They pass by and through each other until at last they have
formed two perfect rings around you.
You see that the beings making up the external ring are facing
outward toward the boundaries of your realm.
Those of the internal ring are facing inward toward you. One by
one, each being in each ring touches the creature beside him.
Now the beings begin to rise into the air.
The two rings of beings revolve around you in opposite
directions.
This bizarre dance of mismatched creatures slowly spinning
around you is the most curious thing you have ever witnessed.
You can't help it, but an amused grin comes over your face.
Your grin lasts only a moment, however, as you see that the
entities that make up the two rings do not share in your
humor.
Their eyes seem troubled and lifeless. They look upon you with
great need and desire.
They are looking for something that only you can give them,
power.
As you read the patterns of energy emanating from the two
circles, you are stunned by how how weak they are.
Help us, help us, they cry out to you.
One by one, their voices are raised, louder and louder, in a
desperate call for assistance.
You know that you must act quickly, for the momentum of the
rings is slowing.
You move to the pools of flow and counter -flow, and draw
from each of them a ball of energy.
energy. You join these balls of energy together.
The power they create is mighty and you hurl it into the
two rings of calling beings to supercharge them.
Nothing happens.
You draw from the pools again and again. Faster and faster you
bombard the rings with intense balls of energy, but they are
still still becoming slower.
In desperation, you turn to the mirror, you hope for an answer,
and you receive one.
In the glass, you can see only your own reflection.
Now you realize what must be done.
With powerful purpose and intent, you soar high above the two
diminishing circles within your realm and look down upon them
there you see it the empty space between the two rings you
know that you must fill this empty space wild energy races
through you but you know that you must remain steady and open
yourself completely to the opposite flows of the two rings you
feel the the balanced energies within these two rings, the flame
and the shadow, the breeze and the storm, the balance that the
elemental portals and the two rings contain.
In a blinding burst of speed, you wing toward your goal.
You enter the gap between the two rings and release your energy.
Your power unites the two rings and accelerates their pace. You
feel the power of the flow and the counter flow as they
speed around you.
The two circles are gaining in strength and meaning and now you
know that your work between them is complete.
You separate yourself from the energy that you have created
between the two rings.
You float away from this energy and enter into the exact center
of the inner ring. ring.
There, you hover and watch and wait.
The rings have now reached an incredible speed. They seem to be
tilting back and forth on some unseen axis.
Suddenly, both rings are not only encircling you, they are also
revolving around you in opposite directions.
One passes overhead as the other passes below you. It is like
being in the center of a gigantic gyroscope.
The strength and power being generated by the spinning rings is
unlike anything you have ever felt before, and your spirit
tingles with excitement.
You feel the balance the rings contain, and you know that the
secrets of these rings are yours for the taking.
You extend your arms and open yourself to the balance and the
power of the rings flying around you.
Streams of flow and counter flow energy begin to enter and move
through you.
As each one passes, you feel more and more attuned to them
and to yourself.
Each wave of energy washes a weight out. Each wave of energy
infuses you with possibility.
You float inside of the two rings with perfect trust and perfect
understanding.
The rings are yours. It is time to seal them and cast
the most powerful circle you have ever known.
With great will you call for the elements and the elementals. A
gale of wind blasts forth from the portal of the east and
swirls about the base of the statue of air. A mighty A
mighty flame shoots forth from the Portal of the South like the
breath of a great dragon and dances about the Statue of Fire.
A great wave of water and emotion washes forth from the Portal
of the West and flows freely around the Statue of Water.
The smell of green leaves and fresh dirt surrounds you as energy
pours from the Portal of the North and green magic grows on
the Statue of the Earth.
you breathe deeply of the elemental energies and ready yourself
to call for deity but the gods and goddesses are already here
a spectral crescent moon floats before you it is steeped in
magic and the ancient mystery of the goddess it lunges towards
you and pierces you just below the heart but you feel no
pain you know that your very soul has been impaled by the
crescent moon moon, and that a piece of it has been taken
from you by the tip of this holy horn.
Your courage has been rewarded, and the spirit of the goddess
herself has blessed you.
The crescent moon slowly raises you upward, and you are filled
with the pleasure of being held by the Great Mother. mother.
The crescent moon slides through your soul and out of your body
and rises high above you.
In a blinding flash, a great glowing ball appears before you and
hangs in the air. The power and light that radiates from it
is like the power of a billion suns compressed into a single
sphere.
A stream of flame bursts from this sphere and burns across your
chest.
You know that the very spirit of the God has touched you.
The glowing ball expands and sweeps upwards towards the crescent
moon and joins with the moon in a brilliant flash of power
and light.
You can feel the peace of your soul in the center of
their union.
You know that this part of your soul is being remade into
something new, something powerful. It is as if a part of you
is being reborn for a reason you do not yet understand.
Billowing vapors begin to swell from this place of creation.
They slowly build into a storm of energy and magic.
Monstrous crashes of thunder and bright flashes of light and
color emanate from the ever growing mass of clouds.
You look hard into the center of the energy storm. What do
you see?
You see that the hands of deity have forged the peace of
your soul into the most beautiful and commanding sword you have
ever seen.
You extend your hand towards the sword, and it spins and races
towards you in a blur of speed.
It pierces the two rings,
crystallizing and shattering them into a billion shards of
glass.
They explode around you at the exact moment the sword reaches
your hand, and you drive the sword down to seal the circle.
You feel the sword penetrate and hold inside some unseen force.
The shattered pieces of the rings fly outward and melt together
and they form two gigantic spheres of crystalline energy around
you.
You stand in the center of your realm in the two spheres.
You are feeling more magical and more powerful than you you ever
imagined you could.
You reach down and wrap your hand around the hilt of the
sword.
You are eager to reclaim it, but the sword won't budge.
You can see that the blade of the sword is half buried
in the center of a huge circle of white marble that has
somehow formed beneath you.
Looking out toward the edge of this new addition to your realm,
you see that a ring of jet That black stone encompasses the
inner circle of white marble. It is slowly spinning in a counter
-clockwise direction.
Again you reach for the soul sword and pull at it with
all your physical and magical might.
Still it refuses to move.
You do not yet possess the strength to claim that sword, a
brusque voice says to you. You look up in time to see
the elderly gentleman slowly sinking back into the pool of the
sun.
Now you hear the gentle voice of the old woman.
Don't despair, dear, she says. Your time will come.
She disappears completely into the pool of the moon.
A soft, calming breeze brushes your forehead. head, relaxing and
refreshing your spirit.
You look around at the vastness of the shadow realm, and are
awed by its power and its beauty.
You know that you have learned much this day, and any feelings
of lack or disappointment flow away from you and vanish
completely.
You know that it is time to rest now, so you sit
down on the circle of white marble at your feet and open
your third eye.
You feel the great circles of power you have cast, intact but
still and quiet around you.
All is calm and at peace within the realm. You are satisfied
with its balance.
You begin to float up toward the reality of the waking world.
Softly, slowly, you float up.
Small doorways melt and form in the walls of the two spheres,
and as you pass through them, you are returning to your human
body and mind.
Softly, slowly, you rise farther and farther away from the
shadow realm. you feel yourself becoming solid again you are
aware of your breath as it enters your lungs and exits again
you take in a deep cleansing breath and as you exhale you
open your eyes and return to the earthly plane
Thank you.